Inventory of the R. Freeman Butts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- LECTURE ARRANGEMENTS AND CONFERENCES
  - "Educational History in the Context of Reform in American Society," A.E.S.A., San Francisco, October 31, 1975
  - Mid-West Philosophy of Education Society and Phi Delta Kappa, Wayne State University, Detroit, November, 1975
  - Bicentennial Lecture Series, Indiana University at Fort Wayne, December, 1975
  - U.S. Office of Education, Regional Conference, Compulsary Education, Kansas City, Missouri, December, 1975
  - George S. Counts Lectue, Southern Illinois University, January, 1976
  - New England Philosophy of Education Society and Phi Delta Kappa, April, 1976
  - University of Tennessee, Knoxville, History of Citizen-ship Education, May, 1976
  - Marburger, Carl, National Committee for Citizens in Education
  - Dan Boorstein and Critical Choices
  - Aspen Institute's Program in Education for a Changing Society, 1975
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1977-1983
  - Correspondence with John Hurst, Berkeley
  - General correspondence, 1976-1984
  - General correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 220)
  - General correspondence, miscellaneous
- PROPOSED REVISION OF The College Charts Its Course (Box 221)
  - Autobiography of "The College Charts Its Course," reassessing "The Education Frontier," American Journal of Education, 1981
  - Chapter 1 - European Liberal Educaiton Transplanted (to 1650)
  - European Liberal Education Transplanted to America
  - Chapter 2 - A Liberal Education Enlightened (1650-, 1779)
  - Chapter 3 - Afterglow of the Enlightenment
  - Enlightenment in American Higher Education
  - Chapter 4 - Preview of the Future
  - Chapter 5 - The Great Resistance (Box 222)
  - 19th Century - Wayland and Mental Discussion
  - Higher Education - Early 19th Century, 1776-1860
- GENERAL
  - Curriculum vitaes, 1975-1981 (Box 223)
  - Carnegie Proposal: Public Education and Political Community, September, 1973
  - Carnegie Addenda, letters of appreciation for writings of R. Freeman Butts, November, 1973
  - N.I.E., proposals for "A Reexamination of American Public Education,", May, 1973
  - Gates, Authur
  - Teachers College, R. Freeman Butts' activities as Head of Department of Social and Philosophical Foundations, 1948-1958 (Box 224)
  - S.S.E.C. - Annual Conference, Citizenship and Teacher Education, June, 1986 (Box 225)
  - Bank St./Teachers College Conference on Progressive Education, October, 1986
  - Wilson Center and A.D.L. Colloquium on Democratic Freedom and Responsibility, February, 1986
  - California Times Radio
  - ETHIKNON
  - Hanna Archivist and Research
  - Hanna Collection, Hoover Institution
  - Hoover National Fellows Program
- THE REVIVAL OF CIVIC LEARNING (Box 226)
  - Phi Delta Kappa, contract, correspondence and reviews
  - Contents and preface
  - Chapter 1 - Challenge of the Privatism in Politics and Pluralism in Education, 1980s:
  - Chapter 2 - The Idea of Citizenship
  - Chapter 3 - Historical Perspectives on Citizenship Education in the Schools
  - Chapter 5 - A Decalogue for Civic Education in the Schools
  - Copies of the Decalogue
  - Decalogue transparency
- GENERAL
  - R.B.S. - Colloquium on History of Citizen Education, April, 1978
  - Society for the Study of Curriculum History, A.E.R.A., San Francisco, April, 1979
  - Wilton Dillon and Smithsonian Symposium on Orwell, December, 1983
    - "History of Citizen Education," Colloquium papers, Philadelphia, April 19-20, 1978
    - "The Dilemma of Civic Learning...," originals, Paper I, Smithsonian Symposium (paper written by R. F. Butts) (Box 227)
    - Paper II, edited texts, September, 1983
    - Eliot Chapple's version of Paper II, November, 1983
    - Papers given at symposium
    - Paper III, delivered, December 9, 1983
    - Paper IV, final version as sent to Chapple, December 16, 1983
  - U.S.O.E., School - Community - House Initiatives
    - Proposal, budget and addresses
    - Handwritten originals (Box 228)
  - San Jose State University, 1976-1978 (Box 229)
    - The Humanities and Civic Education
    - Research ideas
    - Department of Counselor Education
    - N.E.H. Seminar, Summer, 1978
    - Ed. Int. 196A - Education and American Civilization (proposed)
    - Ed. Int. 201 - Critical Issues in Education, (3 folders)
    - Ed. Int. 285 - Colloquium in Contemporary Education
    - Francis Villemain, (2 folders) (Box 230)
    - Bilingual Civic Education, Warren Kallenberg
    - "Democratizing the School of Education Through the Humanities," N.E.H.
    - N.E.H. proposal submitted, March 28, 1978
    - N.E.H. proposal, "Humanities and Civic Education"
    - Class schedules (Box 231)
    - Upcoming speeches and classes
    - N.I.E., Research proposals on Youth Policy Studies, 1978
    - Teacher Corps
    - N.S.F. proposal, November, 1977
  - Southern Connecticutt State College
    - Course in Social Foundations, Spring, 1975
    - American Education to the Bicentennial, Spring, 1976; (2 folders)
  - Santa Clara County Schools
  - Ed. 202E - History of Education in the U.S., 1949-1960
  - TF 4602 - Colloquium in the History of American Education, Spring, 1974
  - San Jose State University (Box 232)
    - Latin American projects
    - Learning Resource Center Based Community Education System (L.R.C.B.C.E.S.)
    - National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education
  - Hoover Seminar on Civic Learning (Box 233)
    - Follow-up, action agenda
    - Follow-up folder
    - Final participant list, December 14, 1984
    - Comprehensive lists of all who were invited
    - Education West Forum, January 16, 1985
    - Introduction to Seminar
    - Publication plans
    - Background materials on Teacher Education for Seminar
    - "Capstone," for The Education Forum, Spring, 1986 (Box 234)
    - Personal report, November 20, 1986
    - Group recommendations and summary of R. F. Butts, November 26, 1984
    - Early drafts from, September 1983 to March 7, 1984
    - Requests for sponsoring organs's to nominate invitees, April 5, 1984
    - Proposed participants
    - Alphabetical invitation lists, May 11, 1984
    - Invitation lists from R. F. Butts
    - Successive invitation lists, May-September, 1984
    - Successive acceptance lists, July-November, 1984
    - Prospectus and letters of invitation, May, 1984
    - Recommendations from groups
    - Drafts of Forum Spread
    - Kennedy's and Mike Atkin's speeches
    - Publicity (Box 235)
    - Education Week, paste-ups
    - Copy for CAC Newsletter
    - Antaeus Report on Seminar
    - Update packet sent following the Seminar
    - Program, early drafts
    - Program, successive drafts
    - Final program and papers, for CAC Newsletter
    - Correspondence relating to Seminar papers, responses and group leaders
    - Seminar papers
    - Working party for follow-up
    - Suggestions to discussion groups
    - Arrangement letters, September 17, 1984
    - Thank you letters
    - A.A.C.T.E. and Hoover Seminar
    - A.A.C. and Mark Curtin on the Hoover Seminar
    - California participants
    - A.E.S.A. on the Hoover Conference (Box 236)
    - Carnegie Foundation and Hoover Seminar
    - Project 87 and Hoover Seminar
    - N.C.S.S. and Hoover Seminar
    - N.E.H. and Hoover Seminar
    - S.P.E. and Hoover Seminar
    - Stanford School of Education and Hoover Seminar
    - Kettering and Hoover Seminar
    - Hoover participants
    - Hewlett
    - Danforth and Hoover Seminar
    - Association of Teacher Education
    - A.B.A. and Hoover Seminar
  - Budget
  - Hoover Controversy, May, 1983 -June, 1984
  - Hoover-Stanford Relations (Box 237)
  - Hoover publicity
  - Hoover events
  - Stanford, visiting scholar, 1976-1978
  - Foundations of African Education, Vol. I and II (Box 238)
  - Education of the West, charts from manuscript (Oversize photo file)
  - Clipping, The New York Sun, Tuesday, April 25, 1939
  - Clipping, Education Week, January 16, 1985
  - Tape 6, "Hoover Seminar on Civic Learning," speeches by Mike Atkin and Donald Kennedy, November, 1985 (Oversize cabinet)
  - 188 slides of Australian schools, 1954 (Oversize cabinet)
  - 53 slides of Puerto Rico, 1958
  - 186 slides relating to South American Teacher Education Study trip, 1963
- The Civic Mission in Educational Reform, 1985-1989
  - Contract, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 239: 1)
  - Reviews for Hoover Press, 1987 (Box-folder 239: 2)
  - Permissions, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 239: 3)
  - Document index, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 239: 4)
  - Working outlines, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 239: 5)
  - Table of contents, 1987 (Box-folder 239: 6-7)
  - Preface, 1987 (Box-folder 239: 8)
  - Introduction to Part I, 1987 (Box-folder 239: 9)
  - Chapter 1, 1987 (Box-folder 239: 10-11)
  - Chapter 2, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 239: 12-14)
  - Chapter 3, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 240: 1-3)
  - Chapter 4, 1987 (Box-folder 240: 4-7)
  - Chapter 5, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 240: 8-11)
  - Chapter 6, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 241: 1-3)
  - Chapter 7, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 241: 4-6)
  - Chapter 8, 1986 (Box-folder 241: 7-8)
  - Chapter 9, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 241: 9-11)
  - Chapter 10, 1987 (Box-folder 242: 1-3)
  - Table of contents and preface, 1988 (Box-folder 242: 4)
  - Introduction to Part I, 1988 (Box-folder 242: 5)
  - Chapter 1, 1988 (Box-folder 242: 6)
  - Chapter 2, 1988 (Box-folder 242: 7)
  - Chapter 3, 1988 (Box-folder 242: 8)
  - Chapter 4, 1988 (Box-folder 242: 9)
  - Chapter 5, 1988 (Box-folder 242: 10)
  - Chapter 6, 1988 (Box-folder 243: 1)
  - Chapter 7, 1988 (Box-folder 243: 2-3)
  - Index, 1988 (Box-folder 243: 4)
  - Proofs, 1989 (Box-folder 243: 5)
  - "The Moral Imperative for American Schools," The American Journal of Education, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 243: 6)
- The Morality of Democratic Citizenship: Goals for Civic Education in the Republic's Third Century, 1987-1988
  - Copyright, 1988 (Box-folder 244: 1)
  - Table of contents and preface, 1987 (Box-folder 244: 2)
  - Late additions to front matter, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 244: 3)
  - Chapter 1, 1987 (Box-folder 244: 4)
  - Chapter 2, 1987 (Box-folder 244: 5)
  - Chapter 3, 1987 (Box-folder 244: 6)
  - Chapter 4, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 244: 7)
  - Footnotes, 1988 (Box-folder 244: 8)
  - Proofs, 1988 (Box-folder 244: 9)
- "The Dilemma of Civic Learning in the Schools of a Pluralist Democracy," paper presented at the Eighth International Symposium of the Smithsonian Institution, 1983 (Box-folder 245: 1-5)
- "Historical Perspective on the Civic Role of the School in American Society," paper presented at the Cooperative German/American Conference on the Civic Education of Youth, 1985 (Box-folder 245: 6-10)
- "The Enduring Basis of Reconciliation: Education," opinion piece submitted to The New York Times (Box-folder 245: 11)
- "Paradoxes in Democratic Values," an extension of remarks made at a session of the National Council for the Social Studies, 1983 (Box-folder 245: 12)
- National Public Radio proposal, 1987 (Box-folder 245: 12)
- WGBH project proposal, 1988 (Box-folder 245: 13)
- MacArthur Foundation correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 245: 14)
- U.S. Department of Education correspondence, 1988 (Box-folder 245: 15)
- Washington trips, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 245: 16)
- Course materials on history and theory of higher education, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 246: 1-3)
- Articles on liberal education, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 246: 4-5)
- Clippings on higher education, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 246: 7-8)
- Evergreen State College conference on alternative education, 1981 (Box-folder 247: 1-2)
- Correspondence with Mervyn L. Cadwallader, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 247: 3-4)
- American Association of Colleges meetings and publications, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 247: 5-9)
- Educational Leadership Project, 1984 (Box-folder 247: 10)
- Correspondence with James A. Perkings, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 247: 11)
- Research materials on liberal education, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 247: 12)
- Meiklejohn Education Foundation correspondence, minutes, and publications, 1984-1988
  - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 248: 1-2)
  - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 248: 3)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 248: 4)
- Correspondence with Sven Groennnings, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 248: 5)
- "What Should We Learn from the History of Citizenship Education in the United States?", 1978 (Box-folder 249: 1)
- Revisionist educational history, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 249: 2-5)
- Course materials on history of education, 1955-1979 (Box-folder 250: 1)
- Clippings for San Jose State University classes, 1977 (Box-folder 250: 2)
- Research materials and notes on cultural revisionism, 1957-1977 (Box-folder 250: 3)
- Clippings and notes on the search for national purpose, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 250: 4)
- Miscellaneous clippings, 1970-1978 (Box-folder 250: 5-6)
- Clippings and notes on goals for secondary and post-secondary education, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 250: 7)
- Recent statistics, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 250: 8)
- Royalty statements and contracts, 1941-1983
  - Harper & Row, Arno Press, and World Book-Childcraft International, 1971-1983 (Box-folder 251: 1)
  - McGraw-Hill, 1941-1977 (Box-folder 251: 2)
- Promotion of The College Charts its Course, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 251: 3)
- A Cultural History of Education, 1947-1955
  - Promotion, 1947 (Box-folder 251: 4)
  - Original draft of introduction, 1947 (Box-folder 251: 5)
  - Correspondence on second edition, 1955 (Box-folder 251: 6)
- The Education of the West, 1969-1977
  - Correspondence with McGraw-Hill, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 251: 7)
  - Marketing information, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 251: 8)
  - Reviews, 1973 (Box-folder 251: 9)
  - Complimentary copies, 1973 (Box-folder 251: 10)
  - Bibliography, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 251: 11)
  - Permissions, 1973 (Box-folder 251: 13)
  - Editorial corrections, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 251: 14)
  - Index, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 251: 15)
- Public Education in the United States: From Revolution to Reform, 1974-1987
  - Reactions, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 251: 1)
  - Marketing information, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 251: 2)
  - Reviewers' comments, 1977 (Box-folder 251: 3)
  - 1984-1987 (Box-folder 251: 4)
  - Copyright, 1976-1985 (Box-folder 252: 5)
  - Outlines and periodization, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 252: 6)
  - Permissions, 1977 (Box-folder 252: 7)
  - Correspondence with Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, 1977-1987 (Box-folder 252: 8)
  - Test questions, 1980 (Box-folder 252: 9)
- Correspondence and royalty statements relating to Foundations of Education series, 1968-1975 (Box-folder 252: 10)
- Colloquium on Issues in University Governance, 1968 (Box-folder 253: 1)
- Statement by Council of Tenured Faculty of Columbia University, 1970 (Box-folder 253: 2)
- Clippings and notes on general crisis of American education, 1970 (Box-folder 253: 3)
- Teachers College materials, 1970-1984
  - Crisis, 1970-1984 (Box-folder 253: 4)
  - Planning committee for faculty conference, 1970 (Box-folder 253: 5)
  - Governance and College Policy Council, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 253: 6)
  - Ad hoc Committee on Governance report, 1971 (Box-folder 253: 7)
  - Emeriti, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 253: 8)
  - Correspondence with Lawrence A. Cremin, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 253: 9)
- Council for the Advancement of Citizenship materials, 1983-1987
  - Board of directors meetings, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 254: 1-6)
  - Jennings Randolph Forum, 1987 (Box-folder 254: 7)
  - Correspondence with Diane Eisenberg, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 254: 8)
- Center for Civic Education board meetings, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 254: 9-10)
- History of Education Society meetings, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 254: 1-2)
- American Educational Studies Association meetings, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 254: 3-4)
- American Educational Research Association, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 254: 5-6)
- Social Science Education Consortium meetings, 1988 (Box-folder 254: 7)
- Society of Professors of Education meetings, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 254: 8)
- Philosophy of Education Society meetings, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 254: 9)
- Far Western Philosophy of Education Society meetings, 1976-1986 (Box-folder 255: 10-11)
- American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education meetings, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 255: 12-13)
- Atlantic Council meetings, 1988 (Box-folder 255: 14)
- School-Community-Home forum, 1979-1986
  - Agenda and papers, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 256: 1-2)
  - "Historical Perspective on the Role of the School in American Society", 1979 (Box-folder 256: 3-4)
  - Additional background materials, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 256: 5)
- Correspondence with David Hackett, 1986 (Box-folder 256: 6)
- Research materials and notes
  - Rise of the civic ideal for education, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 257: 1-3)
  - Family, home, parents, children, and youth, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 257: 4)
  - Women, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 257: 5)
  - Community, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 257: 6)
- People for the American Way materials, 1984-1988
  - Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 258: 1)
  - "Religion, Education, and the First Amendment: The Appeal to History" by R. Freeman Butts, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 258: 2-5)
  - Correspondence with Polly Gault, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 258: 6)
- The Civic Mission in Educational Reform, 1989 (Box-folder 259: 1)
- Writings by others, 1975-1976
  - Steve Arons, 1975 (Box-folder 260: 1)
  - Mary Anner Raywid, 1976 (Box-folder 260: 2)
- Research materials, 1958-1983
  - Multiethnic education, 1973-1983 (Box-folder 260: 3-4)
  - Freedom, 1958 (Box-folder 260: 5)
- "The Search for Freedom," chapter 10 of Public Education in the United States: From Revolution to Reform, 1976 (Box-folder 261: 1)
- Childhood and Government Project, 1975 (Box-folder 261: 2)
- Research materials, 1960-1988
  - First Amendment, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 261: 3)
  - Rights of parents, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 261: 4)
  - Rights of children and youth, 1974-1981 (Box-folder 261: 5)
  - Academic freedom, 1960-1986 (Box-folder 261: 6)
  - Rights of teachers, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 261: 7)
  - Desegregation, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 262: 1-2)
  - Desegregation and busing, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 262: 3-6)
  - Affirmative action, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 263: 1-2)
  - Bakke case, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 263: 3-5)
  - Desegregation and busing, 1974-1985 (Box-folder 263: 6)
  - Educational reform, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 264: 1)
  - Economic inequality, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 264: 2)
  - Compensatory education, 1967-1985 (Box-folder 264: 3)
  - Inequality in financing schools, 1975-1985 (Box-folder 264: 4)
  - Serrano v. Priest, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 264: 5)
  - San Antonio v. Rodriguez, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 264: 6)
  - Vocational education and equality, 1971-1978 (Box-folder 264: 7)
  - Academic achievement, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 264: 8)
  - Political socialization, 1968-1979 (Box-folder 265: 1)
  - Civic knowledge, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 265: 2)
  - Polls on public education, 1974-1988 (Box-folder 265: 3)
- National Assessment of Educational Priorities correspondence and publications, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 265: 4-6)
- Independent Sector meeting, 1982 (Box-folder 265: 7)
- Institute for Research on Educational Finance and Governance papers, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 266: 1-2)
- Research materials, 1965-1989
  - Public education, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 266: 3-7)
  - Political socialization, 1971-1982 (Box-folder 266: 8)
  - Private schools, 1965-1989 (Box-folder 266: 9-11)
  - Student values, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 266: 12)
  - Compulsory education, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 267: 1-2)
  - Public education, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 267: 3)
  - State regulation of private schools, 1976-1986 (Box-folder 267: 4)
- San Jose State University lecture and talk, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 267: 5)
- Talks on vouchers, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 267: 6-8)
- National Academy of Education meeting, 1986 (Box-folder 267: 9)
- University of Virginia symposium on choice, 1986 (Box-folder 267: 10)
- Research materials, 1968-1987
  - Choice and vouchers, 1973-1987 (Box-folder 268: 1-3)
  - California tax revolt, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 268: 4)
  - Tuition tax credits, 1972-1985 (Box-folder 268: 5-6)
  - Values and moral education, 1968-1987 (Box-folder 269: 1-7)
  - Values and moral education, 1978-1987 (Box-folder 270: 1-8)
  - Character, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 270: 9)
  - Violence and vandalism, 1981 (Box-folder 270: 10)
  - Discipline, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 270: 11)
  - Social studies, 1971-1988 (Box-folder 271: 1-3)
  - Citizenship and civic education, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 271: 4-7)
  - Indoctrination, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 272: 1-2)
- National Institute for Citizen Education in the Law correspondence and publications, 1984 (Box-folder 272: 3)
- Citizenship Development Study Project correspondence and reports, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 272: 4)
- Social Science Education Consortium conference papers, 1985 (Box-folder 272: 5)
- Coalition for Law-Related Education memoranda and article, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 272: 6)
- American Bar Association materials on law-related education, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 272: 7)
- National Association of Secondary School Principals correspondence and report, 1985 (Box-folder 272: 8)
- Constitutional Rights Foundation correspondence and publications, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 272: 9-10)
- California Committee on Citizenship Education correspondence and memoranda, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 272: 11)
- Law-Related Education Committee (Santa Clara County) newsletters and reports, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 272: 12)
- National Endowment for the Humanities correspondence and reports, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 272: 13)
- Christian Science Monitor articles, 1986 (Box-folder 272: 14)
- Project '87 correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 273: 1)
- Smithsonian Bicentennial of the Constitution symposium correspondence
- Constitutional Government and the Development of an Enlightened Citizenry conference paper and correspondence, 1986
- Correspondence with Betty Rauch, 1986 (Box-folder 273: 4)
- National 4-H Council correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 273: 5)
- The Civic Mission in Educational Reform, 1989 (Box-folder 273: 6)
  - Final draft, 1989 (Box-folder 273: 6)
  - Background materials and revisions, 1989 (Box-folder 274: 1-6)
- "Historical Perspective on the Role of the School in American Society", 1979 (Box-folder 274: 7)
- Draft of The Revival of Civic Learning: A Rationale for Citizenship Education in American Schools, 1980 (Box-folder 275: 2-3)
- Revised chapters of Public Education in the United States: From Revolution to Reform, 1978 (Box-folder 275: 4-6)
- Atlantic Council Committee on Education and the Successor Generation meetings, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 275: 7)
- American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education Task Force on Civic Learning meetings, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 276: 1-2)
- California Commission on the Teaching Profession reports, 1985 (Box-folder 276: 3)
- Education Commission of the States report on teaching, 1986 (Box-folder 276: 4)
- Articles on teacher education, 1965-1985 (Box-folder 276: 5-7)
- Hoover Seminar on Civic Learning in the Education of the Teaching Profession correspondence and papers, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 277: 1)
- National Commission for Excellence in Teacher Education reports, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 277: 2)
- Civic Education Enhancement Project correspondence, newsletter, and report, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 277: 3)
- Correspondence with David G. Imig, 1981 (Box-folder 277: 4)
- California Association of Colleges for Teacher Education conference, 1978 (Box-folder 277: 5)
- Social Science Education Consortium conference correspondence, program, and paper, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 277: 6)
- Study of Stanford and the Schools correspondence and clippings, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 277: 7)
- Stanford Public Service Center correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 277: 8)
- Institute for Research on Education Finance and Governance correspondence, newsletter, and report, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 277: 9)
- Criticism of other professional schools, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 277: 10)
- Religion, Education, and the First Amendment: The Appeal to History, 1986 (Box-folder 278: 1)
- Miscellaneous articles by R. Freeman Butts, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 278: 2)